如果我们有立体声对，则对应于左眼的图像和对应的图像
If we have a stereo pair, an image that corresponds to the left eye and an image that corresponds
在右眼，如果我们能够提出一种机制来指导这两者
to the right eye, if we can come up with a mechanism for directing those two slightly
不同的图像到各自的眼睛，然后我们有一个非常，非常生动的三维感
different images to the respective eyes, then we have a very, very vivid sense of the three-dimensionality
这是3D电影，3D电视等的基本原理。
of the scene and this is the underlying principle of 3D movies, 3D television and so on.
这是人类最长时间着迷的东西。我真的很喜欢这个
It's something human beings have been fascinated with for the longest time. I really love this
这部电影的海报来自1950年代的电影院。它向我们展示了那里
movie poster in this scene from a cinema back in the 1950's. It shows us that there’s
这种长期的人类对3D电影的迷恋。这不是最近的现象。技术
this long term human fascination with 3D movies. It's not a recent phenomenon. The technology
不断变化，但基本原则完全相同。根本问题
keeps changing, but the underlying principle is exactly the same. The fundamental problem
我们需要解决的是如何将不同的图像分成左眼和右眼？
we need to address is how do we get different image into our left eye and our right eye?
让我们来看看多年来开发的一些技术。
Let’s have a look at some of the technologies that have been developed over the years.
为了再现我们在日常生活中获得的真实生动的3D感知，我们
In order to reproduce the really vivid 3D perception that we get in everyday life, we
需要使用一些相当精细的机制来人为地重建这种效果。
need to use some rather elaborate mechanisms to recreate that effect artificially.
所以第一个可能是从上个世纪初回来的，这个设备的作用是什么
So the first one is back from probably early last century and what this device does is
拍摄对应于来自左眼的图像和拍摄的另一图像的图像
takes an image which corresponds to an image from the left eye and another image taken
从对应于右眼的位置。
from a position that corresponds to the right eye.
然后这个镜头机制将左图像发送到我的左眼和右图像
Then this lens mechanism here sends the left image into my left eye and the right image
进入我的右眼所以如果我把它拿到脸上，我会看到一个非常生动的立体感
into my right eye. So if I hold this up to my face, I see a really vivid three-dimensional
100多年前拍摄的场景的代表。
representation of the scene that was captured more than 100 years ago.
这是第一种立体镜，这些东西真的很受欢迎
This is the first kind of stereoscope and these things were really, really popular in
20世纪初。因此，该技术的稍微更现代的版本是来自
the early 1900s. So a slightly more modern version of that technology is something from
20世纪60年代，这一个在一小块纸板上有许多立体图像对
the 1960s and this one has a number of stereo image pairs on a little piece of cardboard
还有一点点击，所以我可以更方便地从一张图片移动到另一张图片。
and a little clicker so I can move from one picture to the other much more conveniently.
如果我再次把握住这一点，我会对我正在看的场景产生非常生动的3D感知。
If I hold this up to my head, again, I get a very vivid 3D perception of the scene that I’m looking at.
另一种为左眼和右眼提供不同图像的方法是什么
Another approach to providing different images into the left and right hand eyes, what’s
称为浮雕技术，你看红色和蓝色的立体图像
called the Anaglyph Technique and you look at an anaglyph image through red and blue
眼镜。会发生什么是左图像以红色和右手图像打印
glasses. What happens is that the left image is printed in red and the right-handed image
用蓝色印刷，戴上这些过滤后的眼镜，左边的图像就会出现
is printed in blue and by putting on these filtered glasses, the left image comes through
红色滤镜进入我的左眼。它不通过蓝色滤镜。所以我的右眼
the red filter into my left eye. It does not pass though the blue filter. So my right eye
没有看到。对于右手图像，以蓝色打印的图像通过
doesn't see that. For the right-hand image, the one that’s printed in blue, comes through
蓝色过滤到我的右眼，但没有进入我的左眼。所以，如果我把它放在和
the blue filter into my right eye but not into my left eye. So if I put this on and
查看网页上的印刷立体图像或立体图像，例如，NASA有
look at a printed anaglyph image or an anaglyph image on a webpage, for instance, NASA has
很多火星的立体图像，我们得到一个非常非常生动的3D感觉。
lots of anaglyph images of Mars, we get a very, very vivid 3D sensation.
这只是NASA收集的3D立体图像的一张图片。最近的火星
This is just one image from NASA’s collection of 3D anaglyph images. The most recent Mars
流浪者都携带相当复杂的立体视觉系统，图像被传回
Rovers all carry quite sophisticated stereovision systems and the images are transmitted back
到地球，由美国国家航空航天局处理并变成浮雕形式，并通过他们的网站提供。
to Earth, processed by NASA and turned into anaglyph form and made available through their website.
我们没有得到的是一个非常完整的颜色表示，因为我们是
What we don’t get though is a very full representation of the colour because we’re
通过红色和蓝色眼镜看着它。所以它看起来有点单色但是3D
looking at it through red and blue glasses. So it looks a bit monochromatic but the 3D
感知真的很生动。如果你有一副立体眼镜，
perception is really quite vivid. If you’ve got access to a pair of anaglyph glasses,
这些是配有红色和蓝色镜片的眼镜，你可能有兴趣抓住它们，放上它们
these are glasses with the red and blue lenses, you might be interested to grab them, put them
然后看看下面几张图片。它们包含一些非常生动的三维内容。
on and have a look at these next few images. They contain some very vivid three-dimensional content.
绘制3D坐标框架的工具箱功能具有立体模式。如果我们打电话给
The toolbox function that draws 3D coordinate frames has an anaglyph mode. If we call the
我们之前见过的trplot函数，它将以90度的旋转传递
trplot function which we've seen before, it will pass in a rotation of 90 degrees around
X轴，这是我们想要显示的坐标系。我们通过3D图
the X axis so that’s the coordinate frame that we want to display. We pass the 3D plot
选项，如果我通过我的立体眼镜看到这一点，我会得到一个非常逼真的3D印象。
option and if I view this through my anaglyph glasses, I get a very realistic 3D impression.
我实际上看到Z轴有点出现在屏幕外面。
I actually see that Z axis coming out of the screen somewhat.
另一种技术和你在3D电影中看到的技巧，你可以看到重力或阿凡达，霍比特人的东西
Another technique and one you see in 3D movies, you can see Gravity or Avatar, Hobbit, something
像这样，你戴上这样的眼镜，剧院里发生的事情就是左手
like that, and you put on glasses like this, what happens in the theatre is the left-hand
图像是用光投射的，但它可能在垂直方向上也是偏振的
image is projected with light but it’s polarized perhaps in the vertical direction and that
光线通过这个滤光片，让偏振光进入我的右眼
light goes through this filter which lets through polarized light into my right eye
但是没有进入我的左眼，因为这个滤镜在水平方向上是偏振的。
but not into my left eye because this filter is polarized in the horizontal direction.
右手图像是通过此滤镜进行垂直偏振投影的
The right-hand image is projected with a vertical polarization comes through this filter but
不要进入这个过滤器。所以当我把它放在电影院的头上时，我看到了一个非常好的
not into this filter. So when I put this on my head in the cinema, I see a really wonderful
被拍摄的场景的3D五颜六色的表示法。
3D colourful representation of the scene that was filmed.
对于家庭使用，使用三维电视，技术有点不同。
For home use, with three-dimensional TV’s, the technology is a little bit different.
我们使用的是这些液晶快门眼镜。现在发生的是电视
What we use are these liquid crystal shutter glasses. What happens now is that the television
每秒约100次呈现左右图像。我们留下了图像，
presents the left and right images sequentially about 100 times per second. We have left image,
右图像，左图像，右图像和这些眼镜中的镜头同步
right image, left image, right image and the lenses in these glasses are synchronized with
电视，所以当投影左图像时，这个镜头变得清晰，正确，这个
the TV so when the left image is projected, this lens becomes clear and the right, this
一，是不透明的。所以我只看到左眼的左图。然后1/100秒，
one, is opaque. So I only see the left image in my left eye. Then 1/100th of a second later,
正确的图像投射在电视上;这个镜头变黑了，这个很清楚。所以
the right image is projected on the TV; this lens goes black and this one goes clear. So
有了这些，我得到了一个非常生动，又多彩，三维的表现形式
with these on my head, I get a very vivid, again colourful, and three-dimensional representation
通过电视的场景。
of the scene through the TV.
最后的方法是不要试图使用彩色眼镜，过滤眼镜和
The final approach is to do away with trying to use colour glasses, filtered glasses, and
戴在我头上的眼镜，将左右图像直接投射到我的眼睛里。
shuttered glasses on my head and to project the left and right image directly into my eyes.
因此，在某些方面，它是像这样的旧立体观众的高科技模拟
So in some ways it’s a high-tech analog of the old stereoscopic viewers like this
一个和这一个。所以这里是最先进的头戴式显示器。如果我把它放在我的身上
one and this one. So here is the state-of-the-art head-mounted display. If I put this on my
头部，左侧图像通过这个镜头直接投射到我的左眼和眼睛
head, the left image is projected through this lens directly into my left eye and the
右手图像通过这个镜头直接投射到我的右眼。
right-hand image is projected through this lens directly into my right eye.
我们所看到的所有技术都要求我们在头上戴上东西
All of the techniques that we’ve looked at require us to wear something on our head
这并不总是很方便。也许我们没有特定的眼镜
and that’s not always very convenient. Maybe we don’t have the particular glasses to
手或者我们发现它妨碍了我们的日常生活。
hand or maybe we find that it gets in the way of our everyday life.
所以在尝试创建立体声效果时需要做很多工作
So there’s been quite a bit of work in trying to create the stereo effect without needing
你有什么想法，所以最近的一项创新就是所展示的技术
to have anything on your head, so one fairly recent innovation is the technology shown
这里有图解。它要求你的头部距离大约正确
diagrammatically here. It requires that your head is approximately the right distance away
从屏幕上看，有一个透镜系统折射左手的光线
from the screen and there is a system of lenses which refract the light from the left-hand
左眼大致方向的图像和右手图像被折射
image in the general direction of your left eye and the right-hand image is refracted
在你的右眼的大方向。
in the general direction of your right eye.